<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Technological Sovereignty - Democratising technology and innovation</title>
    <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech" />
    <updated>2020-01-22T21:12:31+01:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech</id>

    <entry>
        <title>6. Annex 1: DiEM25 Guiding Principles on Technology Policy</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/6-annex-1-diem25-guiding-principles-on-technology-policy.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/6-annex-1-diem25-guiding-principles-on-technology-policy.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-21T20:48:23+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    1. Technology serves humanity, not the other way around.What&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h4 id="mcetoc_1dv4qc4ol9" class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>1. Technology serves humanity, not the other way around.</strong></span></h4>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>What does that mean?</i></strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Technological development is not a goal in itself. Technology exists to serve human progress. When technology harms humanity, it should be regulated, restricted, or even banned. And all aspects of humanity, such as welfare, health, ease of use, values, and social relationships of all humans have to be taken into account.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>DiEM25</strong> firmly supports human rights in the face of technology – humans, all humans, come first, and technology second.</span></p>
<p class="p2"> </p>
<h4 id="mcetoc_1dv4qc1f68" class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>2. Technology can be awesome.</strong></span></h4>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>What does that mean?</i></strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Technological development can be a formidable force for good. Technology is a key contributor to our civilisation’s ability to provide health, welfare, social interaction, freedom, safety and happiness. Technology allows for the increases in productivity enabling human progress.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>DiEM25</strong> firmly supports sound and positive technological development that benefits mankind, and rejects Luddite anti-technological thinking.</span></p>
<p class="p2"> </p>
<h4 id="mcetoc_1dv4qbul37" class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>3. There is always a choice.</strong></span></h4>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>What does that mean?</i></strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Every technological development is the result of choices. Choices made by governments, investors, consumers, manufacturers, distributors and many others. No technology is god-given or invisible hand-given. No technology is unavoidable or un-opposable.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">DiEM25 believes that, as a society, we have the duty to be aware of the fact that we make choices on technology. Choices on technical standards. On interoperability. On ownership and use of technology. On control and regulation of technology. Those choices, and the debate around them, must become visible to the public eye, and exposed on the public platform.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>DiEM25</strong> firmly supports democracy and rejects technocracy.</span></p>
<p class="p2"> </p>
<h4 id="mcetoc_1dv4qbrgp6" class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>4. There is no such thing as a free lunch.</strong></span></h4>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>What does that mean?</i></strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Everything comes at a cost. Also technology. There are at least three inherent costs of technology. The first cost is that every technology requires initial investment. When that investment comes from the state or another collective body, it must be recognised and rewarded. The second cost is that, by selecting or benefitting one technology over another, someone always loses out. It is a hidden cost, paid by the beneficiaries of the technology we choose not to develop. The third is the cost related to creating and using a technology. From pollution to traffic victims, many people pay a heavy price for technology.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">D<strong>iEM25</strong> wants society to recognise the costs of technology to society, in addition to its benefits. Then, both costs and benefits need to be properly allocated and/or compensated.</span></p>
<h4 id="mcetoc_1dv4qbnd35" class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>5. Value is in sharing</strong></span></h4>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>What does that mean?</i></strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Technology is the result of value creation, and, in turn, enables the creation of more value. But value does not stand by itself. Value exists in relation to other things, and to people. Artificial boundaries that block or slow down the creative sharing of technology damage society. The more value and technology are shared, the more they can create value in return. By sharing technology and knowledge, society ensures that much more value is created than by “protecting” it. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">D<strong>iEM25</strong> firmly supports sharing technology, and rejects monopolies or rent seeking.</span></p>
<h4 id="mcetoc_1dv4qbgoe4" class="p1"><span class="s1"><br> <strong>6. There is no natural distribution of the proceeds of technology</strong></span></h4>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>What does that mean?</i></strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">The “invisible hand” is a dogma, and it does not actually exist. The proceeds of technology originate from the whole of society – no inventor is an island. Sharing the proceeds of technology across society is a matter of essential fairness. This is because non-regulated systems are structurally incapable of providing a fair and just distribution of the proceeds of technology. Therefore, we must establish rules on how the proceeds of technological process benefit all different parts of society. That is a quintessential democratic process: the clash of different interest groups must be done openly, through debate, with enforceable rules of engagement. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>DiEM25</strong> strongly believes that the decision on allocation of the proceeds of technological development must be openly and democratically discussed. <strong>DiEM25</strong> firmly rejects the dogma of the invisible hand.</span></p>
<p class="p2"> </p>
<h4 id="mcetoc_1dv4qbcoj3" class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>7. We stand on the shoulders of giants</strong></span></h4>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>What does that mean?</i></strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Technology does not fall from the sky. For tens of thousands of years, humans have made incremental progress in developing technology. It is the result of collaboration and co-operation between many. The knowledge handed down from our ancestors is absolutely necessary for us to build on it. And just like we borrowed that knowledge from our ancestors, we need to pass it on to the next generations. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>DiEM25</strong> rejects artificial boundaries around knowledge, and wants to ensure that continued progress remains possible through the sharing of both old and new knowledge.</span></p>
<h4 id="mcetoc_1dv4qb8932" class="p1"><span class="s1"><br> <strong>8. No-Frankenstein-principle</strong></span></h4>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>What does that mean?</i></strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Our society is becoming ever more complex, as is our technology. 50 years ago, a well-trained engineer could understand, and repair, a lot of technology. That is no longer the case. With hyper-specialisation comes hyper-mutual dependency. Sometimes we don’t fully understand the technology we create. Therefore, the myth of the sole genius (e.g. Dr. Frankenstein) solving a fundamental problem in his (never, by the way, “her”) basement is no longer useful – quite the opposite. The ever-increased specialisation and complexity of technology makes it necessary for our society to open up as much information as possible about how things work – so we are able to understand what goes wrong when something goes wrong. As it inevitably will.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>DiEM25</strong> rejects the Frankenstein myth as a workable basis for developing and maintaining knowledge and innovation. An ever more complex and specialised society and technology demands as much open knowledge and communication as possible.</span></p>
<h4 id="mcetoc_1dv4qb4u81" class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>9. Technology reflects our values</strong></span></h4>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>What does that mean?</strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Technology is never value-free. The way we fund, adopt, use and regulate technology, or not, reflects society’s choice of its values and priorities. E.g. we currently accept that thousands of children are killed every year through society’s incoherent approach to the use of transportation technology. That is a reflection of our society’s priorities and values. We must be more aware of how choices around technology must be rooted in values, and openly discuss and decide on them in a democratic way. The agenda setting of the debate around technology and values should be open, and not set by the technology industry itself.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>DiEM25</strong> strongly supports open and healthy discussions on the values that are reflected through our choices around technology, and firmly rejects the notion of value-free technology. Negative values such as corruption, fraud or privilege are not acceptable, and technology may not be used to defend or strengthen them</span></p>
<h4 id="mcetoc_1dv4qb01b0" class="p1"><span class="s1"><br> <strong>10. Technology solves technical problems, not human ones</strong></span></h4>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong><i>What does that mean?</i></strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Technological messianism is not the right approach. Technology is a tool that can help to solve technical problems. But it is humans who must direct how technology is used, and its purpose must be to solve human problems and the problems of all lifeforms that humans are responsible for. Justice, equality, fairness, or the lack thereof, will not be solved by technology alone. Without human and moral guidance, technology has as much opportunity to make problems worse as to make them better. Already, we see how prejudice and bias can be strengthened through technology, making technology part of the problem, rather than the solution. In the end, technology is and remains a tool. And we must choose how to use it.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>DiEM25</strong> believes that technology must be used as a tool to address problems of human society, and firmly rejects technological messianism.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>5.2. Review Process</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/52-review-process.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/52-review-process.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-21T20:47:11+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Technology changes rapidly today. In addition, DiEM25 is aware&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">Technology changes rapidly today. In addition, DiEM25 is aware that, while we have endeavoured to cover as many fields of technology as possible, this paper has its main focus on Information Technology. Many other technologies (health and biotech related, new materials, energy, space and aviation, defense, CRISPR and other aspects of genetic technology, GMOs, IoT, VR/AR, Cybersecurity and encryption, and many others) merit attention as well. However, many policies in chapter 2 and chapter 3 address structures, such as innovation funding, that can apply across most technological domains. The focus on Information Technology does make sense, however, from the observation that “information” and the way it is handled, are key to any political system.<br> </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">While Annex 1 provides guiding principles on how more specific answers in any field of technology can be formulated on the basis of this paper, it may not be sufficient. To address these two challenges – rapidly changing technology, and the inevitable need to address additional topics and perspectives – DiEM25 will carry out regular reviews of this paper.</span></p>
<h4 id="mcetoc_1dv4q9pf60" class="p1"><span class="s1"><br> <strong>The review will be on an annual basis, unless there is a meaningful event or request from the membership to speed up that process.</strong></span></h4>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">The review process will be lead by the Technological Sovereignty 1 DSC, and will take place annually in spring. It will consist of the publication of a questionnaire to the membership, asking for meaningful input in terms of modifications or new developments. If a discovery or scientific development makes any of the proposals substantially obsolete or contrary to our goals (for example, if cryptography is broken, or some equally cataclysmic event), it will be amended – corrected as soon as possible.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Based on the input received, an editing team will suggest modifications, updates or new additions to the Paper, and the updated version will be subject to a new vote of the membership. Depending on the complexity of the material received, this process may happen in one or two iterations, and additional feedback of the membership may be asked. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">If no sufficient material changes are suggested, it is possible that no update is provided, in which case the previous version remains applicable.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">This process will be done in a transparent manner; all steps of the process will be shared with the membership, and a procedure will be set up to ensure that, in case of disagreements, a transparent and open decision process will be used.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>5.1. Approval Process</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/51-approval-process.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/51-approval-process.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-21T20:46:46+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is the 2019 version of DiEM25’s Technological Sovereignty&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">This is the 2019 version of DiEM25’s Technological Sovereignty Green Paper. It will be subject to a vote of approval of the whole membership. Once approved, it will officially be published as a White Paper and becomes part of DiEM25’s Progressive Agenda for Europe.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>5. Approval and Review Process</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/5-approval-and-review-process.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/5-approval-and-review-process.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-21T20:46:34+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    The review process for this Greenpaper will be outlined&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                The review process for this Greenpaper will be outlined in the following sections.
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>4.3. And What Would the World Feel Like?</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/43-and-what-would-the-world-feel-like.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/43-and-what-would-the-world-feel-like.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-21T20:45:29+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                     Diane, 29, Estonia Diane is a junior developer&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong> <img class="post__image post__image--left" src="https://pktch.github.io/tech/media/posts/40/image6-23.png" alt="Diane" width="185" height="186">Diane, 29, Estonia</strong></span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Diane is a junior developer with a considerable skill set. After she landed some newbie gigs with bigger transnational companies she felt both overworked and under-challenged, so she decided to join a bunch of developers who have committed to working toward a green transition. Her job was to develop an app for people that buy and sell home-generated-electricity – cooperatives similar to Paul’s, in Berlin. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">After a short while she realised that this is not a mission which attracts a lot of start-up capital, as it was not the principal aim of the app to generate quick revenue. Luckily she discovered an EU funding scheme for research and innovation that was deliberately aimed at civil society organisations, non-profit technology projects and cooperatives with a clear mission of green and social change. The funding helped her to develop the app and a sustainable business model that provides enough money for the three developers that now maintain and further develop the app. </span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">The app is – of course – licensed under a Free and Open Software license so other cooperative can tailor it to their needs. Or have Diane and her team do it for them.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>4.2.2. European Innovation Foundation for the Common Good</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/422-european-innovation-foundation-for-the-common-good.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/422-european-innovation-foundation-for-the-common-good.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-21T20:44:55+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Instead of waiting for Silicon Valley to be in&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">Instead of waiting for Silicon Valley to be in charge of technological breakthroughs for private gain, Europe should invest in shaping technological breakthroughs for the common good. This organisation shall envision, coordinate and conduct research and innovation into <strong>technologies for the common good, for democratic governance and ownership of technologies</strong>. It will be governed by the European parliament and European citizen assemblies. It will have the political mandate to foster innovation for the common good, such as achieving the Paris Agreement’s goals, the UN Sustainable Development Goals and other principles for the common good as agreed in the EU.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">The foundation may only invest in projects that are based on democratic ownership and governance. Its success is measured not in patents, economic growth or other commercial indicators but by the increase in quality of life of present and future generations. We propose several initial focus areas:</span></p>
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1"><span class="s2"><strong>Labour Intelligence</strong>: An institute for innovation in automatic decision making in cooperation with workers, which shall explore and prototype intelligent systems with various axes of worker control (i.e. ranging from 'systems designed along worker-friendly principles' to 'responsive to real-time worker input' to 'explicitly incorporating cooperative decision mechanisms for key decisions').</span>
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1"><span class="s2">It shall partner with existing organisations, in particular cooperatives (platform and otherwise), to apply and test systems under real-world conditions.</span></li>
<li class="li1"><span class="s2">It shall assess outcomes with particular attention to humanistic goals, quality of life and environmental sustainability, and worker-centered perspectives, emphasising the dignity and autonomy of workers.</span></li>
<li class="li1"><span class="s2">It shall require particular attention to barriers faced by marginalised workers and workers from traditionally excluded backgrounds.</span></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li class="li1"><span class="s2"><strong>Technology for Democratic Processes: </strong>An institute to explore how technological tools can support democratic processes and citizen participation, for example assessing the potential of various digital voting platforms.</span></li>
<li class="li1"><span class="s2"><strong>Sustainable Technologies</strong>: An institute for innovation around sustainable and widely accessible technologies for a fast and just ecological transformation.</span></li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>4.2.1. Levelling the Playing Field for Platform Cooperatives</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/421-levelling-the-playing-field-for-platform-cooperatives.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/421-levelling-the-playing-field-for-platform-cooperatives.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-21T20:43:58+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Digital technologies can help to create new and more&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">Digital technologies can help to create new and more democratic organisational forms for economic activity and for governing infrastructures. Very promising ideas and developments are ongoing in the movement for <strong>platform cooperatives</strong> where the aim is to make workers, users and other stakeholders the <strong>owners of platforms</strong> that coordinate economic activities, e.g. taxi drivers owning and operating their own digital platform to constrain the dominance of platform monopolies.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Effective taxation and regulation will pave the way for the development of platform co-operatives – models of economic exchange which are owned and governed by workers, users and other stakeholders and often have social and ethical objectives. Instead of trying to imitate Silicon Valley, the EU must strive to create a democratic and collaborative digital economy that has social justice and environmental justice hardwired into its structures. </span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>4.2. Democratising the Economy</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/42-democratising-the-economy.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/42-democratising-the-economy.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-21T20:43:39+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    To democratise research and innovation we also need to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">To democratise research and innovation we also need to find ways to democratise the economy and to foster more decentralised economic arrangements, collective decision-making and structures for shared responsibilities. In short, we need to democratise economic decision making and ownership of technology and organisations. DiEM25’s labour pillar addresses the need for worker participation in companies. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Digital technologies are already being used to coordinate and to govern economic processes. This hints at a big opportunity to shape economic systems in the 21st century. We need to democratise these technological capabilities, and and shift their application from the accumulation of profit to a radically different challenge: to shape economies that foster social justice and help to keep our production and consumption within planetary boundaries. Technologies such as the Internet of Things, robotics and machine learning offer vast potential to transform how we coordinate our lives and activities. <strong>It is imperative that this revolution in coordination is democratic at its heart</strong>. If not, technological authoritarianism will further emerge.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>We must envision how ideas for real progress, such as that of an “economy for the common good”, can be implemented and democratically governed in such systems. Concretely this boils down to questions such as: whose values and interests will program automated traffic systems, smart grids for sharing energy or automated agricultural technologies, and who will benefit from these technological powers? The capacity of these technologies is too vast to remain in private hands. It must belong to citizens. </span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>4.1.3. Participatory Budgeting Platform for Research and Innovation</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/413-participatory-budgeting-platform-for-research-and-innovation.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/413-participatory-budgeting-platform-for-research-and-innovation.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-21T20:43:12+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    We propose a digital platform for participatory budgeting on&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">We propose a digital platform for participatory budgeting on a transnational level. This platform will be a 21st century institution that democratises the funding of research and innovation within the EU, giving citizens and civil society a stronger say.</span></p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dv4q2ggt0" class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>Democratise Funding: Citizen Crowdfunding </strong></span></h3>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">The platform needs to contain a crowd funding system that allows European citizens to allocate public money, e.g. from the EU’s “Horizon Europe”, through their decisions on the platform. The projects apply with their proposals and a sum of money that would allow them to start the work. As in crowdfunding, if enough citizens allocate public money to a proposed project it is successful and gets money from the fund. A significant proportion of public funds for research and innovation needs to be put into this platform to give citizens a voice. </span></p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dv4q2l6t1" class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>Democratise Agenda Setting: Citizens’ Needs Crowdsourcing </strong></span></h3>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">Innovation starts with problems that should be solved. Who defines the problems is a major issue in every innovation journey. In a democratic society, citizens should define the problems that innovations should help to solve. Therefore, the platform should also enable citizens to identify problems to be addressed through research and innovation. Problems would be freely submitted, then democratically ranked on the platform. Researchers and innovators can then apply with proposals targeting specific problems. In this way, <span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>purposes for innovation can be democratically defined by citizens rather than steered by unaccountable private interests.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>4.1.2. EU Funding for Purpose before Profit</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/412-eu-funding-for-purpose-before-profit.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/412-eu-funding-for-purpose-before-profit.html</id>

        <updated>2020-01-21T20:42:46+01:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    We need to fund social and cultural innovation in&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">We need to fund social and cultural innovation in concert with technological innovation. Different forms of creativity and transformation need to be combined to move into a brighter future, and funding should be distributed among a broader group of recipients. EU funding for research and innovation must be more easily attainable for civil society organisations, non-profit technology projects, cooperatives and others with a clear mission of green and social change. We need to fund purpose before profit from public money. There must furthermore be democratic oversight of the funding process. The EU should hold <strong>stakeholder assemblies</strong> for each funding instrument, involving citizens, researchers, NGOs and others in assessing impact. </span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Furthermore, the returns to research and innovation funding should recognise and support the public life and public institutions on which they depend, e.g. universities, and the collaboration and collective creativity that made them possible. Today if a product is innovated with EU funding the profits of its marketisation are completely privatised.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>We propose that a dedicated percentage of returns from these publicly-supported products contribute to the fund for the <strong>universal basic dividend</strong> as set out in DiEM25’s European New Deal. This gives society a fair return on its public investment in technological development. </span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
