<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Technological Sovereignty - Democratising technology and innovation</title>
    <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech" />
    <updated>2019-10-16T23:01:54+02:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech</id>

    <entry>
        <title>3.1.8. General Reforms to IPs and their Tax Regime</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/318-general-reforms-to-ips-and-their-tax-regime.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/318-general-reforms-to-ips-and-their-tax-regime.html</id>

        <updated>2019-10-16T21:18:15+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    DiEM25 wants to limit the enforcement of IP rights so that it benefits the actual inventor/creator, not their assignees/licencees when they do not contribute economic&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">DiEM25 wants to limit the enforcement of IP rights so that it benefits the actual inventor/creator, not their assignees/licencees when they do not contribute economic value. This will increase the inventor/creator's recognition, and ensure that they actually benefit from the IP monopoly that government creates for them.</span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">Finally, DiEM25 wants to abolish any tax incentives to create, transfer or collect IP rights, and create a special tax on the rental income of existing IP rights as a contributory funding for the Universal Basic Dividend as proposed in the European New Deal.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>3.1.7. Reform Patents </title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/317-reform-patents.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/317-reform-patents.html</id>

        <updated>2019-10-16T21:19:11+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    DiEM25 wants to open a debate on the patent system: should it be abolished, or should it be reformed so that it can fulfill its&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">DiEM25 wants to open a <strong>debate on the patent system</strong>: should it be abolished, or should it be reformed so that it can fulfill its original ambition of rewarding inventors and sharing the ir knowledge and innovations throughout society?</span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">In any case, it should become much easier and cheaper to disable a patent when it does not cover something that is actually novel.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>3.1.6. Reform Copyright</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/316-reform-copyright.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/316-reform-copyright.html</id>

        <updated>2019-10-07T01:56:26+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    DiEM25 wants to fundamentally alter the approach to copyright. This includes the harmonisation of exceptions to copyright, by introducing a "fair use" concept with broad&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">DiEM25 wants to fundamentally alter the approach to copyright<strong>. </strong>This includes the harmonisation of exceptions to copyright, by introducing a "fair use" concept with broad application, based on <strong>freedom of speech</strong>. </span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">In addition, DiEM25 proposes a fundamental reform to the Berne Convention on Literary and Artistic Works of 1886, by updating it and making it suitable for the digital age. This includes measures such as making copyright subject to registration, and payment of a fee that increases with time, forcing collecting authorities to provide full transparency on the rights they claim to represent, the costs they charge, and how much they pay to the right holders, and reversing the burden of proof in copyright: unless something can be shown to be clearly under copyright, it must be in the public domain.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>3.1.5. Tackling Planned Obsolescence</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/315-tackling-planned-obsolescence.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/315-tackling-planned-obsolescence.html</id>

        <updated>2019-10-07T01:55:24+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Planned obsolescence is the practice of designing and selling products with an artificially limited useful life. They are programmed to break down much earlier, and&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">Planned obsolescence is the practice of designing and selling products with an artificially limited useful life. They are programmed to break down much earlier, and repair is made expensive, so consumers need to replace them.<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>This leads to a substantial amount of waste. In line with our ecological goals we want products that are durable, repairable and/or upgradeable. In practice, this means the following: </span></p>
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li1"><span class="s1">Consumers should have the option to have their devices repaired by an independent party. Any documentation or product guarantees that prohibit this should be banned.</span></li>
<li class="li1"><span class="s1">As a general rule, all spare parts should be replaceable, and available on the market. If the original manufacturer no longer provides such spare parts, they cannot block anyone else from providing them.</span></li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>3.1.4. Principles of “Right to Repair” and “Open Standards</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/314-principles-of-right-to-repair-and-open-standards.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/314-principles-of-right-to-repair-and-open-standards.html</id>

        <updated>2019-10-07T01:54:21+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Right to RepairDiEM25 will introduce a fundamental "Right to Repair": the buyer of a product or service has the right to repair any aspect thereof&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <h3 id="mcetoc_1dmhnss700" class="p1"><strong>Right to Repair</strong></h3>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">DiEM25 will introduce a fundamental "<strong>Right to Repair</strong>": the buyer of a product or service has the right to repair any aspect thereof (or have it repaired for them) and IP rights cannot be used as a means to block such Right to Repair. The Right to Repair includes the right to alter the technical standard in which something is made or captured. This means that if you buy something in one technical standard, you have the automatic right to convert it into another technical standard.</span></p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dmhntdit1" class="p1"><strong>Open Standards</strong></h3>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">DiEM25 will introduce the principle of <strong>Open Standards</strong>. Technical standards must be documented so that interoperability is ensured, and they may not be subject to IP monopolies. </span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>3.1.3. Free and Open Knowledge and Licensing </title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/313-free-and-open-knowledge-and-licensing.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/313-free-and-open-knowledge-and-licensing.html</id>

        <updated>2019-10-07T01:51:45+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Any technical development, including software code, that is funded by public money should be made available under licenses equivalent to Free and Open Software licenses.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">Any technical development, including software code, that is funded by public money should be made available under licenses equivalent to <strong>Free and Open Software licenses.</strong> (Note: DiEM25 does not have any a priori preference for any category or set of licenses. We are aware that there is a whole ecosystem of software and creative commons licenses, and, depending on context and the area, the choice of the appropriate license will have to be made. We do not believe in a "one size fits all" approach in this context.)</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">This has several benefits: it provides for independence from non-EU based suppliers, it increases the security and stability of the software and it breaks the de facto monopoly of many technical platform providers.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">While exceptions can be possible under strict circumstances, any such exceptions must be accompanied by a practical mechanism to ensure returns to the public from the proceeds of any monopoly granted. For example, the EU might require that any spin-off created to monetise the result of publicly funded research has to grant, on incorporation, 20% of its shares as non-voting shares to the authorities that funded the research.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">In addition, DiEM25 wants to put barriers around the public domain and prevent the enclosure of the <strong>commons of knowledge</strong>, by establishing certain areas of knowledge outside the reach of IP rights. This will include a ban on the concept of IP rights on anything invented or created by machines, and the introduction of a principle that any information "found in nature" will be and remain at all times in the public domain. Biological information carriers such as DNA or RNA must be classified as "Open Content" languages, and not subject to any IP right.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>3.1.2. Public Money, Public Code </title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/312-public-money-public-code.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/312-public-money-public-code.html</id>

        <updated>2019-10-07T01:50:25+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    With immediate effect, public authorities must switch, where possible, to using Free and Open Source software. Any patent on software functionality may only be awarded&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">With immediate effect, public authorities must switch, where possible, to using Free and Open Source software.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Any patent on software functionality may only be awarded subject to full disclosure of all source code related thereto.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Public funding of Free and Open Source software platforms or core technologies should be envisaged.</span></p>
<h3 id="mcetoc_1dmhnm9nh0" class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>Mid- and Long-term Measures</strong></span></h3>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">The mid and long-term measures around Intellectual Property are all based on the same principles:</span></p>
<ul class="ul1">
<li class="li2"><span class="s1">the cycle of “socialising costs and privatising benefits” that currently exists must be broken </span></li>
<li class="li2"><span class="s1">the privatisation of benefits through the state-enforced monopolies of Intellectual Property rights must be reduced in terms of scope and duration</span></li>
</ul>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">Innovation that is funded by public money should remain accessible to all, by default under the most permissive license systems. In practice, we propose the following principles and practical steps.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>3.1.1. Fair IP Rights</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/311-fair-ip-rights.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/311-fair-ip-rights.html</id>

        <updated>2019-10-07T01:46:45+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Reversing the tax treatment of IP is the easiest immediate step to take. This means that any preferential tax treatment of royalties or other income&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1"><strong>Reversing the tax treatment of IP</strong> is the easiest immediate step to take. This means that any preferential tax treatment of royalties or other income (rent) deriving from IP, such as lower tax rates or higher exemptions on such income, must immediately be withdrawn. They should be replaced by the opposite: income from IP (rent) must be taxed preferably at higher rates, and more progressively, than income from selling actual goods or services.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">In addition, the draft EU Copyright Directive must be fundamentally reviewed, in order to obtain much more balanced rights of users, re-users, creators and innovators. A European "<strong>fair use</strong>" concept must be created, with broad applications, and based on the fundamental<span class="Apple-converted-space">  </span>principle of freedom of speech.</span></p>
<p class="p2"><span class="s1">Introduce a general principle of IP release: any IP belonging to a legal entity which either goes bankrupt, is liquidated or otherwise ceases to function, must be released into the public domain. Equally, any IP ceases to be valid on the death of the inventor/creator.</span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>3.1. Transforming Intellectual Property (IP)</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/31-transforming-intellectual-property-ip.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/31-transforming-intellectual-property-ip.html</id>

        <updated>2019-10-07T01:47:28+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Intellectual Property (IP) is a system of government-created and -enforced exclusive rights (legally created monopolies) on certain aspects of creativity and innovation. They include e.g.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">Intellectual Property (IP) is a system of government-created and -enforced exclusive rights (legally created <strong>monopolies</strong>) on certain aspects of creativity and innovation. They include e.g. patents, copyright, trademarks, trade secrets, database rights and other similar rights.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">There are two standard justifications for IP: recognition and reward. The reward justification argues that IP protects the creator or innovator, by providing them a monopoly that is limited in time and scope, so they can benefit from the ability to recover their investment. After a time, the monopoly lapses, and the invention or creation becomes part of the public domain — i.e. the classical freedom of enterprise, where everything that is not forbidden is allowed, regains its normal place in the market. The recognition justification consists of the argument that IP recognises creators and inventors, and their contribution to society.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">There are a number of problems with IP today.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">First, there is the continued <strong>expansion </strong>of the monopoly rights. Copyrights, originally 18 years long, now last at least until 70 years after the death of the last contributing author (and for Disney a bit longer). Patents used to be for narrow, technical applications (“downstream” aspects of technology), but now apply ever more to “upstream” aspects of technology: methods (i.e. ideas), protocols, discoveries (e.g. in the field of biology), software and many other aspects that used to be non-patentable. In addition, the standards for "novelty" are sometimes laughable. To give a classic example, in Australia, after a patent law reform, someone managed to obtain a patent on the novel invention of the "wheel". Furthermore, new IP rights are invented on a continuous basis — examples include database rights, trade secrets, performers rights and the new secondary copyright for publishers in the draft Copyright Directive.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">The public domain is under continuous attack from privateers.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Second, the link between the creator/innovator and the IP right is no longer functional. The full transferability of IP rights has the practical effect of allowing <strong>hoarding</strong> of monopoly rights to the place in the economic value chain where they produce the least benefit: with marketers and distributors. The actual creators/innovators typically get little to no benefit from or recognition for their contributions.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">The consequences are seriously problematic. For example, while public money provides for most Research and Development (R&amp;D) in developing new drugs, we see that the R&amp;D budget of large pharmaceutical companies is a fraction of their marketing budgets, and most of their R&amp;D budget is spent on researching "me-too" patents: patents on slightly different versions of drugs that already exist, in order to artificially extend their monopoly position (and charge higher prices). It is a classical example of socialising the cost and risk of developing new drugs, while privatising the benefits. The same is true for other innovations and research at universities and other research centres funded with public money. Far too often, the results of such publicly funded research are privatised, often in opaque and non-transparent ways, through the creation and transfer of IP rights to privately held spin-offs.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Third, IP rights have a number of negative effects on the economy and society. The rent they extract generates huge transfers of money to a limited number of corporate monopoly holders and their shareholders. This leads to a very regressive income distribution and <strong>drives economic inequality</strong>, as people who work pay rent to those who hold government-created monopolies on the proceeds of that work. In addition, in many countries IP monopolies enjoy tax exemptions or preferential treatment. This allows large multinationals to shift their profits and benefit from tax forum shopping, driving further inequality as these revenues are hoarded rather than taxed and redistributed for the public good.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">IP rights, today, seem to significantly <strong>slow down innovation</strong>. Through IP claims, large established businesses use ever-growing monopoly rights to block access to their market to newcomers or competitors. Initiatives like the draft Copyright Directive allow copyright to be used as a way to censor content, further reducing the freedom of communication that the Internet originally promised.</span></p>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">In the discussion on the draft EU Copyright Directive, the monopoly holders of content (the entertainment industry) are fighting with the monopoly holders of the tech industry. But who defends the interests of consumers, citizens and creative people?</span></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>3. Free Knowledge for Democratic Innovation – the Role of Intellectual Property and Education</title>
        <author>
            <name>DiEM25 Tech Collective</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://pktch.github.io/tech/3-free-knowledge-for-democratic-innovation-the-role-of-intellectual-property-and-education.html"/>
        <id>https://pktch.github.io/tech/3-free-knowledge-for-democratic-innovation-the-role-of-intellectual-property-and-education.html</id>

        <updated>2019-10-07T01:43:01+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Innovation depends on high quality public life and public services. Creative societies and economies need the infrastructure to support them: well-functioning education and research systems,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p class="p1"><span class="s1">Innovation depends on high quality public life and public services. Creative societies and economies need the infrastructure to support them: well-functioning education and research systems, guaranteed protection of rights and various other forms of state support such as targeted monetary subsidies. Knowledge has always been a product of human collaboration. Our vision of technological change must reflect these needs, and contribute to public life and the common good in turn. </span></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
